<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<gamedesign>
  <HEAD>
    <TITLE>ChessWar</TITLE>
    <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="chesswar.css"/>
  </HEAD>
  <GameName>ChessWar</GameName>
  <license>
    <author>Kalle Marjola</author>
    <year>1991, 1994, 1997, 2002</year>
  </license>
  <license>
    <author>Robert Ramsay</author>
    <type>
      <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">
        Attribution-Share Alike 3.0 Unported
      </a>
    </type>
    <year>2009</year>
  </license>
  <history>
    This is a revised version of original <dt>ChessWar</dt> board game.
    Special thanks to Rami Laaksonen (the original playtester),
    J.C. Klice (most valuable help for the new version), and other
    playtesters and people at Alter Ego. Not for commercial use, all
    rights reserved by the author.
  </history>
  <summary>
    <div class="image">
      <img src="figs/pic_battle.jpg" width="300" height="275"
        alt="Two fully assembled armies set on the battle field"/>
      <caption>
        A small but sturdy dwarf army is confronted by a huge ratmen
        horde.
      </caption>
    </div>
    ChessWar is a strategic game for two players. It is meant to be played
    on a standard chessboard with standard chess pieces although it can also
    be used on any kind of battlefield made of squares. It is NOT chess with
    dice and some extra rules! Instead, it is strategic game played with chess
    pieces. So, pieces are not automatically captured, some pieces (units)
    have ranged attacks and all your pieces (units) may move during your
    turn.
    Required Components:
    <ul>
      <li>Chess board or similar squared board</li>
      <li>Chess pieces, preferably two sets</li>
      <li>One or more six-sided dice (referred as d6 from now on)</li>
    </ul>
    Object in ChessWar is similar to standard chess: Defeat enemy king,
    called general or warlord etc. in ChessWar. The main difference is
    that in this game, all units of each army can move each time the
    player has his turn.


    <I>
      Note: For simplicity all references to players are made with 'he'.
      Readers may substitute she instead of he in all places.
    </I>

  </summary>
  <units>
    <summary>
      All chess pieces are used to represent some kind of unit of your army.
      This unit type depends on the selected army, as in ChessWar, you can
      choose to play elf, dwarf or even scary undead army!
    </summary>
    <unit>
      <dt>King</dt>
      <dd>
        The king represents your king, warlord or general and his
        heartguards.
      </dd>
    </unit>
    <unit>
      <dt>Queen</dt>
      <dd>
        Queen represents mighty wizard or similar magician of your
        army.
      </dd>
    </unit>
    <unit>
      <dt>Rooks</dt>
      <dd>
        represent your catapults, siege engines or giant
        troops. Rooks usually have long range support attacks.
      </dd>
    </unit>
    <unit>
      <dt>Bishop</dt>
      <dd>
        Bishop represents your archers or other similar ranged
        units.
      </dd>
    </unit>
    <unit>
      <dt>Knights</dt>
      <desceription>
        represent your cavalry, was it 20 knightmen with war
        horses or two dozen wolf riders. Some armies do not have knights at
        all.
      </desceription>
    </unit>
    <unit>
      <dt>Pawns</dt>
      <dd>
        Pawns represent your core army, is it 50 pikemen, beastmen or
        fearsome zombies and skeletons.
      </dd>
    </unit>
  </units>
  <attributes>
    <summary>
      Each unit has certain attributes which are used to represents its
      combat abilities:
    </summary>
    <attribute>
      <dt>Move</dt> is speed of the unit. Unit may move up to this number
      of squares each round in normal conditions. Movement can be done
      laterally or diagonally.
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
      <dt>Save</dt> represents the toughness and morale of the unit. In many
      situations, a <dt>save roll</dt> is called. The unit must then roll this
      number or greater with d6. Sometimes this roll is modified by
      some number, but in any case, <dt>roll 1 always fails</dt>. Note that if
      the modified save roll requires you to roll 7 or more, it simply
      cannot succeed.
    </attribute>
    <attribute>
      <dt>Melee</dt> is unit close-combat skill and is used to modify melee
      combat rolls.
    </attribute>
    <note>
      In addition to these basic attributes, some units have special
      abilities like bows or spells. These are explained later on.
    </note>
  </attributes>
  <armies>
    <summary>
      Following armies are currently available in ChessWar. Exact
      composition of each army is provided at the end of the rules.
    </summary>
    <dt>Chaos</dt>
    <dd>
      the dreadful and evil army of Chaos Lords come from the
      Chaos Wastes far beyond any civilization. The army includes lots of
      potent close combat units but is usually few in numbers. like the
      army, their foul chaos magic is aimed for destruction and attack, not
      defense.
    </dd>
    <dt>Dwarves</dt>
    <dd>
      slow but tough, all dwarf units are heavily armored
      and powerful in close combat. Their real weakness is in speed as they
      have no cavalry and all units are very slow because of their small
      feet.
    </dd>
    <dt>Elfs</dt>
    <dd>
      from the deep forest come the race of pointy-eared
      fellows. Unlike other armies their basic infantry are all armed with
      bows, filling the sky with long arrows. And when the enemy army
      closes, the excellent cavalry and mighty treemen can stop it in tracks.
    </dd>
    <dt>Humans</dt>
    <dd>
      the armies of the human kingdoms and empires has
      perhaps the most versatile army, with possibility to yield lots of
      cavalry, bows, catapults or plain infantry, backed with wide variety
      of spells.
    </dd>
    <dt>Orcs</dt>
    <dd>
      the green-skinned big and tough but a bit slow and stupid
      warriors of the barren lands are fierce opponent, coming in great
      numbers and taking lots of punishment. Along their army come
      regenerating, acid-womiting trolls and the fastest cavalry of the
      world, Wolf Riders.
    </dd>
    <dt>Ratmen</dt>
    <dd>
      from underground caves and tunnels arrive a race of
      human-like big rats with long legs and many relatives. Rats come in
      vast hordes, but have no real artillery nor cavalry. However, even the
      basic infantry is far faster than melee infantry of the other armies,
      except for the long-legged elfs with their bows.
    </dd>
    <dt>Undead</dt>
    <dd>
      Last but not least, the scary undead army led by an
      undying liche lord arrives from the lost cities and cemetaries.
      Only the bravest can stand the unnatural horrors of the living dead
      who walk the earth again. But if the opponent can overcome the fear of
      the dead, they find that normal zombies and other undead units are
      very weak and slow in combat.
    </dd>
  </armies>
  <gameplay>
    <ol>
      <h2>Starting the Game</h2>
      <li>Choose race</li>
      <dd>
        Both players must select which race they will use (Human, Elf, Dwarf..).
        Choice could be made secretly or openly, as players like and players
        may have army of same race as opponent's (but this is not
        recommended). It is also recommended that players reveal their choice
        before proceeding to next step.
      </dd>
      <li>Choose army</li>
      <dd>
        After player has chosen which army he will be using, player selects
        the composition of the army he is using. Each army always has one
        general and then pre-determined amount of points, which are used to
        pick various units for the army. Players are encouraged to use all
        points they have, any remaining ones are simply lost.  Army
        composition is not revealed to other player until set-up is
        over. Practically phases 2 and 3 can be done at the same time.
      </dd>
      <li>Set-Up</li>
      <dd>
        Both players deploy their army in first three rows in board on their
        half. Some kind of cardboard is recommended to 'split' the board so
        neither player can see where his opponent deploys.
        After the deploy is done, the cardboard is removed.
      </dd>
      <li>Determine starter</li>
      <dd>
        The game is started by the army with smaller initiative number (order
        is: elf, human, dwarf, chaos, orcs, ratmen, undead). If both players
        have selected the same race, both players roll a d6 and higher one
        (reroll ties) decides which one goes first. The player not starting
        the game can then re-arrange his entire set-up any way he chooses,
        staying in first three rows, before the other player takes the first
        turn.
      </dd>
    </ol>
  </gameplay>
  <div class="h2">
    <div class="pic300">
      <img src="figs/pic_lord.jpg"  width="300" height="250"
        alt="Nice miniatures"/>
      <i>
        The chaos lord has lost all its retainers and now makes the last
        desperate charge against human army.
      </i>
    </div>
    <h2>Playing the Game</h2>
    <p>
      Gameplay in ChessWar is played in <I>rounds</I>. During each round,
      each player takes his turn, moving all his troops and attacking with
      them, in turn order described below. After each player
      has taken their turn, a new round starts. The game lasts
      until either general is dead.
    </p>
    <h3>Turn Sequence</h3>
    <p>Each turn is divided into 3 separate parts that cannot be mixed.</p>
    <ol>
      <li>Movement phase</li>
      <li>Shooting phase</li>
      <li>Melee phase</li>
    </ol>


    In movement phase all units able to move in player's army may be
    moved. In shooting phase all units armed with some kind of ranged attacks
    may fire them at enemy, and in melee phase all units in hand-to-hand
    combat can attack enemy troops in same melee combat.


    Order in each phase is not fixed nor simultaneous. Player may do his
    actions one at the time, for example choose target by result of previous
    shot done by his other unit.


    Spells can break the normal flow of the game, but otherwise player
    cannot react on the turn of the other player.


  </div>
  <div class="h2">


    <h2>
      <a name="movement">Movement phase</a>
    </h2>


    Each turn, player is allowed to move every unit in his army which is
    <dt>not</dt> currently in melee. Each unit may move up to number of
    squares equal to its <dt>move</dt> characteristic and is allowed to
    make a special charge-move after that. If the unit has move of 0,
    it cannot move at all, but can charge enemy units which are next to
    it.


    Each move is to any adjacent square (including diagonally), but the unit
    cannot move from square adjacent to particular enemy to other square
    adjacent to that same enemy. However, the unit can first move away
    and then return to be next to the same enemy.


    <table>
      <tr valign="bottom">
        <td>
          <IMG src="figs/cw_f1.png" width="77" height="77"
           alt="movement diagram"/>
        </td>
        <td>
          <I>
            An unit cannot move from one square next to enemy to any square
            next to same enemy.
          </I>
        </td>
        <td>
          <IMG src="figs/cw_f2.png" width="77" height="77"
           alt="movement diagram"/>
        </td>
        <td>
          <I>
            The same applies to enemy situated diagonally to
            unit.
          </I>
        </td>
        <td>
          <IMG src="figs/cw_f3.png" width="77" height="77"
          alt="movement diagram"/>
        </td>
        <td>
          <I>
            However, the unit can first move away and then return to
            different square next to same enemy.
          </I>
        </td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <h3>
      <a name="charge">Charge</a>
    </h3>
    <p>
      After the unit has moved it is free to charge any one opponent
      adjacent to it. Following rules apply:
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li>
        Charge can be a diagonal one only if squares on both sides are
        either empty or occupied by own units.
      </li>
      <li>
        Unit which is not <dt>brave</dt> can only charge <dt>scary</dt>
        unit if it first succeeds in <I>save roll</I>. If the save fails,
        the unit is stopped in its tracks and cannot move anymore this
        turn. See special attributes for further details.
      </li>
    </ul>


    If the charge is successful, place the unit on edge of its square
    toward the enemy, and do likewise with the enemy. Both units are now
    in melee and neither can leave it until either side is destroyed.


    If the target is already in melee with other unit this does not stop another
    unit attacking it, just place the unit on the edge of square. Now
    target must destroy all its opponents before it is free to move.


    <table>
      <tr valign="bottom">
        <td>
          <IMG src="figs/cw_f6.png" width="77" height="77"
            alt="charge diagram"/>
        </td>
        <td>
          <I>
            An unit can charge any enemies laterally, or even diagonally
            if side squares next to both units are empty.
          </I>
        </td>
        <td>
          <IMG src="figs/cw_f7.png" width="77" height="77"
            alt="charge diagram"/>
        </td>
        <td>
          <I>
            An unit cannot charge diagonally if either side square has
            an enemy unit. The unit can always charge laterally.
          </I>
        </td>
        <td>
          <IMG src="figs/cw_f8.png" width="77" height="77"
            alt="charge diagram"/>
        </td>
        <td>
          <I>
            Own units do not prevent the unit from charging
            diagonally.
          </I>
        </td>
      </tr>
    </table>


  </div>
  <div class="h2">


    <h2>
      <a name="shooting">Shooting Phase</a>
    </h2>

    <div class="right">


      <!-- <object data="figs/cw_f4.eps" type="application/postscript">
     <object data="figs/cw_f4.png" type="image/png">
   Apparently this does NOT work, at least with mozilla. *sigh*
   Maybe I will find some day other way to go around this.
-->

      <img src="figs/cw_f4.png" width="128" height="128"
           alt="shooting diagram"/>

    </div>
    <p>
      Some units are armed with some kind of ranged attack like bows,
      catapults or large boulders. They are allowed to fire at one enemy
      unit in this phase with their weapons unless they are in melee.
    </p>
    <p>
      Shooting is started by selecting the target unit to attack.
      Target for attack must be within range of weapons and
      visible by firer or other unit in their army if weapon can be fired
      <EM>indirectly.</EM> Visibility is determined from
      center of firer's square to center of target's square; any square that
      is crossed by this line blocks the visibility if any unit is in that square.
      If this line crosses exactly between two squares, firer is free
      to choose which one of these two squares is crossed.
    </p>
    <I>
      The black unit marked with A can clearly see white unit 1. It
      can also see unit 2 as the line of sight crosses two
      squares and the empty one can be selected. It cannot see
      unit 3 as other black unit blocks the line of
      sight. However, as another black unit sees unit 3,
      indirect fire can be used. White unit 4 is not seen by
      any black unit and cannot be targeted even indirectly.
    </I>
    <h3>
      <a name="shotintomelee">Shots into Melee</a>
    </h3>
    <p>
      It is dangerous to attack melee combat as units are completely mixed
      up. Thus, whenever a ranged attack (bows, catapult, spell) hits
      an unit in melee combat, roll a d6:
    </p>
    <div class="simpletable">
      <span class="value">5-6:</span> the original target is hit<BR/>
      <span class="value">3-4:</span> the original target and one random
      opponent is hit<BR/>
      <span class="value">1-2:</span> one random opponent is hit!<BR/>
    </div>
    <p>
      If any unit in the melee is destroyed, other combatants do not get a
      free follow-up move.
    </p>
    <h3>
      <a name="bows">Bows</a>
    </h3>
    <p>
      Bows are basic ranged weapon for troops. When fired, select any target
      unit within <dt>4</dt> squares seen by firer or any other friendly unit,
      and roll to-hit. The basic target number to be rolled on a d6
      depends on the shooting unit and is marked in unit statistics. Following
      modifiers apply:
    </p>
    <div class="simpletable">
      <span class="value">-1</span> the firer moved during movement phase<BR/>
      <span class="value">-1</span> the range is 3 or more squares<BR/>
      <span class="value">-2</span> the target is not visible to firer (i.e. indirect fire)
    </div>
    <p>
      If target is hit, it must make its <dt>save</dt> or it is destroyed.
      Note that the roll 6 does not always hit. Remember that if the target
      was in melee and was hit, you must roll if you hit your own
      unit!
    </p>
    <h3>
      <a name="catapults">Catapults</a>
    </h3>
    <p>
      Catapults are heavy siege engines which have unlimited range and can be
      fired indirectly, althought the target square must be seen by at least
      one unit of the same army. However, catapults have minimum range of 2
      squares, they cannot be aimed to square next to catapult
      itself!
    </p>
    <div class="right">
      <table class="box">
        <tr>
          <td align="center">1</td>
          <td>1 square over</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="center">2</td>
          <td>1 square right</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="center">3</td>
          <td>1 square short</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="center">4</td>
          <td>1 square left</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="center">5-6</td>
          <td>no scatter</td>
        </tr>
      </table>
    </div>
    <p>
      To fire a catapult, select a target square seen at least by one own
      unit, and then roll 2 (direct) or 3 (indirect) <I>scatter</I> rolls,
      checking the table on right.
    </p>
    <p>
      The direction is aligned according to the shooting player and the board,
      i.e. number 1 is one square toward the other end of the board.
      The order of the dice is not important, just handle all scatter rolls.
      So if you roll 2 and 5, the final result is one square right of target
      square. Or if you roll 1 and 3, it hits the original
      square.
    </p>
    <p>
      The scatter rolls <dt>can</dt> make the shot to fall short or even on
      the top of the catapult itself! However, if the shot
      falls in the catapult square, it is just a miss.
      If the shot ends out of the gaming board, it is a complete miss.
    </p>
    <p>
      Any unit in the target square is hit and must make its save or
      it is destroyed. If the target hit was in melee, you must
      roll if the catapults hits the other side of the melee as described
      above.
    </p>
    <p>
      <dt>Rocks</dt> and <dt>plaguebombs</dt>: these special catapults have
      maximum range of 2 but no minimum range and always
      scatter just once (except in <I>storm</I>), even when
      used indirectly. The unit can move before making the
      attack and it does not affect the accuracy.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div class="h2">
    <h2>
      <a name="melee">Melee Phase</a>
    </h2>
    <p>
      Any own unit in melee can now attack one enemy unit in same melee.
      Each attack is done one by one and the unit may opt not to attack.
      To make an attack, roll a d6 and add attacker melee modifiers and
      deduct defender melee. Then look at melee result table:
    </p>
    <table class="box">
      <tr>
        <td align="center">6 or more*</td>
        <td>Defender is destroyed.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td align="center">
          5
        </td>
        <td>
          Defender must make 2 saves or it is
          destroyed. <dt>Brave</dt> defender must only save once.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td align="center">4</td>
        <td>Defender must make its save or it is destroyed.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td align="center">2-3</td>
        <td>Stand-off, the melee continues</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td align="center">1 or less</td>
        <td>
          Attacker destroyed unless save is made.<BR/>
          <dt>Scary</dt> attacker must only save if the defender is <dt>brave</dt>
        </td>
      </tr>
    </table>


    * a natural roll 6 always causes this result regardless of any
    modifiers. However, if the defender is <dt>scary</dt> and the attacker
    is not <dt>brave</dt>, refer to result 5.


    If the defender is destroyed, the attacker can then make a follow-up
    move providing it is no longer in melee. This follow-up move is
    either:
    <ul>
      <li>
        Move to square originally occupied by the enemy just
        destroyed. Lateral move is only possible if neither side
        square contains enemy unit, <I>or</I>
      </li>
      <li>
        Perform one <a href="#charge">charge move</a>, using the normal rules (must save if
        charges <dt>scary</dt> unit etc.)
      </li>
    </ul>
    <p>
      The follow-up move is done after all other effects are handled, like
      <I>Plague</I> or <I>Heal spell</I>. Units with move of 0 can only
      make follow-up charge, not move.
    </p>
    <p>
      On a result 1 or less the defender cannot make the follow-up move, nor
      can follow-up move be made if the melee combatant is destroyed in
      the shooting phase or by other unit.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div class="h2">
    <div class="pic300">
      <img src="figs/pic_catapult.jpg" width="300" height="250"
       alt="Battle in action"/>
      <i>The human catapult is surrounded by advancing dwarven warriors.</i>
    </div>
    <h2>
      <a name="special">Special attributes</a>
    </h2>
    Units can have various special attributes, marked in their statistics.
    <dl>
      <dt>Assault</dt>
      <dd>
        When this units charges into melee during movement phase
        it gains +1 to its Melee value for
        this turn. Thus, if the unit normally has Melee -1 it has Melee +0
        when it charges. If the unit itself is charged, the unit makes
        follow-up move or the melee continues, this bonus does not apply.
      </dd>
      <dt>Bows</dt>
      <dd>
        The unit is armed with bows and can use them to shoot in
        the shooting phase. Refer to shooting rules. The to-hit number
        is given for each unit with bows.
      </dd>
      <dt>
        <a name="sa_brave">Brave</a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
        The unit is very brave (or just stupid) and ignores special attribute
        <dt>scary</dt>. In addition, brave units perform better in melee combat
        (result 5).
      </dd>
      <dt>
        <a name="sa_catapults">Catapults</a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
        The unit has catapults (or similar siege weapons) and can fire
        them in shooting phase as explained in main rules.
      </dd>
      <dt>
        <a name="sa_crossbows">Crossbows</a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
        Crossbows are like <dt>bows</dt> but are limited so that they
        cannot be fired indirectly nor cannot be fired if the unit moved
        in movement phase.
      </dd>
      <dt>
        <a name="sa_longbows">Longbows</a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
        As bows, but refer to elite elven archers with maximum range of 5
        squares instead of normal 4 squares.
      </dd>
      <dt>
        <a name="sa_plague">Plague</a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
        Unit is infected with plague; if it is destroyed while in melee all
        units in melee with it may have caught the plague and must make
        their save at +1 or are destroyed. This unit is also immune to
        any kind of plague.
      </dd>
      <dt>
        <a name="sa_plaguebombs">Plaguebombs</a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
        The unit has poisoned bombs. These are used as catapults, but have
        maximum range of 2 squares, can be thrown to square next to attacker,
        and always rolls just one scatter die (even if used indirectly).
        Any unit in target square must
        make save at +1 unless is immune to <dt>plague</dt>. If target was
        in melee, it and all its opponents are hit!
      </dd>
      <dt>
        <a name="sa_regenerate">Regenerate</a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
        When the unit is destroyed, just topple it over. If any unit moves to
        its square, remove it from the game, but otherwise at the
        end of the turn, the unit regenerates on a d6 roll 3+ and is bought
        back to battle. If the roll fails, remove the unit from
        the game. This unit can never be raised as zombies, but it spreads
        plague normally. Any new hits to unit are ignored when it is
        lying on the ground.
      </dd>
      <dt>
        <a name="sa_rocks">Rocks</a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
        Giant boulders hurled by trolls or giants are counted as
        special catapult attack, with no minimum range but max range of 2
        squares and 1 scatter always (even indirectly).
      </dd>
      <dt>
        <a name="sa_scary">Scary</a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
        This unit is very frightening. Any unit (which is not <dt>brave</dt>)
        wishing to charge this unit must make its save or its movement
        ends and it cannot enter melee this turn (but it may fire normally).
        In addition, <dt>scary</dt> affects melee combat table unless the other
        side is <dt>brave</dt> (results um 6 and 1)
      </dd>
      <dt>
        <a name="sa_spells">Spells</a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
        The unit can cast spells. Refer to <a href="#magic">magic section</a>.
      </dd>
      <dt>
        <a name="sa_teleport">Teleport</a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
        The unit moves via teleporting. Just move the unit up to its maximum
        move squares, ignoring any intervening units. The unit can
        move away from melee combat this way. Any charge move is
        done after the teleport move.
      </dd>
      <dt>
        <a name="sa_terrorpults">Terrorpults</a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
        These units have normal catapults except that they fire ammunition
        with shrieks and screams, causing supernatural terror. Target hit
        is automatically destroyed unless it is <dt>brave</dt>. Brave targets
        must make a normal save to survive.
      </dd>
      <dt>
        <a name="sa_undead">Undead</a>
      </dt>
      <dd>
        These units are really dead. They are automatically <dt>brave</dt> and
        <dt>scary</dt>. In addition, <dt>plague</dt> does not affect
        them and they get +1 at any saves against bows (including Longbows and
        Crossbows)
      </dd>
    </dl>
  </div>
  <h2>
    <a name="magic">Magic</a>
  </h2>
  <p>
    Most armies can include some kind of wizard in their force which is
    capable of launching devastating spells.
    Each wizard can cast <dt>one</dt> spell each turn. The spell is normally
    cast on own turn, but the wizard can cast an <I>instant</I>
    spell on enemy's turn - if it does so, it cannot cast a spell in
    players's next turn.
  </p>
  <p>
    Most spells are always successful, unless the other side tries to
    <I>counterspell</I> them, but some require a success roll.
    The wizard can cast same spell again and again, but choice of spells
    is limited by actual type of wizard (see <a href="#lists">army lists</a>).
    In addition, each spell has its own restrictions about when it can be
    cast:
  </p>
  <dt>Instant</dt> spells can be cast anytime, even on enemy's
  turn! Any action currently being done is interrupted by the spell.
  However, if the dice is already rolled, its effect happens.
  <dt>Move</dt> spell is cast immediately after the wizard has moved.
  It cannot be cast if the wizard is in melee (exception: flight on
  himself).

  <dt>Shoot</dt> and <dt>melee</dt> is cast in appropriate phase, when the
  wizard is about to attack. Note that wizard in melee combat
  cannot cast a shoot spell.
  <p>
    In addition, some spells are classified as <dt>temporal</dt> and
    after being cast, they last until start of the wizard's next turn.
    If the wizard is killed, however, the effect immediately ends.
    Note that cumulative temporal spells have no extra effect, except that
    they are harder to dispel (several dispels are needed). Thus, it is
    not harder to shoot while 2 <I>storm</I> spells are in effect but both
    need to be dispelled before the shooting can be done unhindered.
  </p>
  <dl>
    <dt>
      <a name="s_contagion">Contagion</a>
    </dt> (move, temporal)
    <dd>
      This unit makes all own units carriers of powerful plague. All own
      units have special ability <dt>plague</dt> until start of wizard
      player's next turn unless effect is dispelled. Consult
      <a href="#special">
        special attributes
      </a>.
    </dd>
    <dt>
      <a name="s_counterspell">Counterspell</a>
    </dt> (instant)
    <dd>
      This spell can be cast at any time when another spell is just cast,
      including another Counterspell. The target spell is dispelled on a d6
      roll 4+ and has no effect. Note that if Counterspell is countered,
      the original spell works. The counterspell is rolled after any spell
      working rolls are made (Heal, Counterspell) but before any derivated
      rolls are made (Strike and Zap! effects)
    </dd>
    <dt>
      <a name="s_dispel">Dispel</a>
    </dt> (move)
    <dd>
      This spell dispels any temporal magic spell
      (Contagion, Fear, Protection or Storm). If several temporal spells
      are in effect, this spell only dispels one of them.

    </dd>
    <dt>
      <a name="s_fear">Fear</a>
    </dt> (move, temporal)
    <dd>
      All own units are <dt>scary</dt> until start of the wizard player's
      next turn. Consult <a href="#special">special attributes</a> for
      effects of scary. Note that this spell does not make them <dt>brave</dt>.
    </dd>
    <dt>
      <a name="s_flight">Flight</a>
    </dt> (move)
    <dd>
      This spell can be targeted on any unit visible to wizard.
      The unit is counted as having special attribute <dt>teleport</dt>
      and <dt>brave</dt> until end of the movement phase and move of 4.
      However, the unit can only move to a square visible to the wizard
      when casting this spell. Note that the wizard can use this spell
      on himself, and as (<dt>exception</dt> to normal rules) can cast
      it to itself even when in melee.
    </dd>
    <dt>
      <a name="s_heal">Heal</a>
    </dt> (instant)
    <dd>
      <p>
        This spell can be cast at any time on unit within 2 squares
        of the wizard, even not in sight, which was just destroyed.
        On a d6 roll of 4+ the unit is healed and it can continue on
        fighting. If used in melee, the attacker cannot naturally advance to
        square of the healed target.
      </p>
      <p>
        This spell can be cast on the wizard itself if the wizard is
        destroyed. If target had <dt>plague</dt> and is saved, other combatants
        do not need to save against it.
      </p>
    </dd>
    <dt>
      <a name="s_protection">Protection</a>
    </dt> (move, temporal)
    <dd>
      This spell creates force field around wizard and all 8 adjacent
      squares. All <dt>own</dt> units within that area gain +1 to their
      saves, become <dt>brave</dt> and are immune to <dt>plague</dt> as
      long as they remain in area (or arrive to it). Effects for
      multiple <I>protections</I>  are not cumulative.
    </dd>
    <dt>
      <a name="s_raisedead">Raise Dead</a>
    </dt> (instant)
    <dd>
      <p>
        This spell has range of 4 and can be targeted at any non-undead
        unit which just has been destroyed (it does not need to be visible).
        The target unit is immediately raised as new zombie unit and joins the
        Undead army, but cannot move or shoot until player's next turn.
      </p>
      <p>
        The raised unit is a normal zombie unit except if the destroyed unit
        has <dt>assault</dt> in which case undead cavalry is raised, or if
        the unit had <dt>bows</dt> (or longbows but not crossbows) an undead
        bowmen are raised, or if the unit had <dt>catapults</dt>, an undead
        catapults are raised. If Undead is already using maximum number of
        special Undead units, normal zombies are raised.
      </p>
      <p>
        Any heal spell is tried before this spell can be used. Regenerating
        unit cannot be raised. If own unit destroyed in melee is raised,
        any enemy unit in melee with old unit stay in melee with the new
        one.
      </p>
    </dd>
    <dt>
      <a name="s_storm">Storm</a>
    </dt> (move, temporal)
    <dd>
      <p>
        Wizard summons a powerful storm which hinders all ranged attack
        until start of wizard player's next turn.
      </p>
      <p>
        Any bow attacks, including crossbows but excluding rocks, are
        at -1 to-hit per each square of range instead of normal range modifiers.
        Catapults (including plaguebombs) are at extra scatter die for each 2
        squares of range.
      </p>
    </dd>
    <dt>
      <a name="s_strike">Strike</a>
    </dt> (melee)
    <dd>
      Instead of attacking a melee target in the melee phase the wizard
      may cast this spell and force one opponent to make its save at
      -2 or it is destroyed.
    </dd>
    <dt>
      <a name="s_zap">Zap!</a>
    </dt> (shoot)
    <dd>
      <p>
        This spell can be cast by wizard exactly like ranged attack
        (so wizard may not be in melee). It has range of 4, it cannot
        be targeted indirectly and it strikes target automatically,
        which must make its <dt>save</dt> or it is destroyed. If targeted
        at melee, remember <a href="#shotintomelee">
          to roll
        </a> which target
        is hit, after all.
      </p>
      <p>
        Appearance of this spell is always different: Human wizards
        prefer fireballs and lightning bolts, elves like thorn sprays
        while orc shamans cause a gigantic foot of their god to trample
        on enemy.
      </p>
    </dd>
  </dl>
  <div class="pic250">
    <img src="figs/pic_zombies.jpg"  width="250" height="200"
     alt="Fierce melee"/>
    <i>Elven cavalry has been attacked by scary zombies.</i>
  </div>
  <h2>Extra Rules</h2>
  <dt>ChessWar</dt>
  <dd>
    can be expanded beyond normal chessboard and
    pieces. This section gives possible ideas on how to expand the
    game. Note that these ideas and rules have not been tested out.
  </dd>
  <h3>Custom Gameboard</h3>
  <dt>ChessWar</dt>
  <dd>
    can be played on any square-based game board, it needs
    not to be a standard 8x8 chess board. If using a larger game
    board, catapult (including Terrropult) range should be limited
    to 8 squares.
  </dd>
  <p>
    The non-standard game board can also include terrain like forest or
    hills. Any extra terrain can be added as agreed by the players.
  </p>
  <div class="simpletable">
    <dt>Forest</dt> blocks visiblity like an unit but can be
    moved into. The unit in forest is visible normally but
    has +1 saves against ranged attacks and if charged, attacker
    loses any <dt>assault</dt> bonus.

    <dt>Hill</dt> blocks visiblity like units or forest. However, any unit
    on the hill can see over any units (but not forest or
    hills), and can likewise be seen.
  </div>

  <h3>Total Massacre</h3>


  <dt>ChessWar</dt> is normally played until either general (king) is
  dead. With these rules the game lasts until either side is wiped
  out. However, following rules apply as soon as own general is
  lost:
  <ul>
    <li>
      All enemy units are counted as being <dt>scary</dt>
    </li>
    <li>
      Melee units cannot make the free follow-up move
    </li>
    <li>
      Indirect fire cannot be used
    </li>
  </ul>

  With <dt>Undead</dt> army, in addition to the above rules (well, first
  one really does not affect them)
  they also lose one <dt>undead</dt> unit of their choice at the start of
  their turn until has none left.

  <h3>Multi-Side Fights</h3>


  When playing with custom gameboard, there could be enough room to
  handle multiple armies. In such a case, each army acts one by
  one as using normal rules. Total massacre rules should be used
  so that not any army just disappears.


  The game can also be played like 2 armies versus other two. In  such a
  case, both armies of the same side should act at the same
  time. Total massacre rules should be used, but the side which
  first kills both generals of the other side is immediate winner.

  <h3>Extended Armies</h3>


  The game can be played with larger armies. Use whatever method agreed
  by the players, but remember that point costs are not comparable, even
  when the armies have same number of build points as generals are worth
  different points. Thus, the fairest way to extend armies is to double
  the points (and maximum number of units of each type) and give each
  player 2 generals.


  When an army has 2 (or more) generals, all of them must be defeated
  before the army is defeated. It is assumed that one of the generals is
  the supreme commander and the rest are second-in-command who take
  control if the first one is slain.

  <h2>Army lists</h2>


  Each army has given initiative rating (the lowest goes first) and points
  to select other pieces than the general which is always taken.
  All units in each army are in standard order; king first (K), then queen (Q),
  rook (R), bishop (B), knight (N) and finally pawns. Dwarf and Ratmen
  armies do not have knights at all. Attributes for each unit are:

  <dl>
    <dt>Max:</dt>
    <dd>
      maximum number of this kind of units
      in army. The final army before set-up may not have more units of
      this type
    </dd>
    <dt>Cost:</dt>
    <dd> cost in points per unit of this type</dd>
    <dt>
      Move:
    </dt>
    <dd>
      maximum squares that unit can be
      move per movement phase (excluding charge)
    </dd>
    <dt>Save:</dt>
    <dd>
      saving throw. A d6 roll which must be
      made for unit to survive most hits or to charge scary target
    </dd>
    <dt>Melee:</dt>
    <dd> modifier to melee rolls</dd>
    <dt>Special:</dt>
    <dd> any special abilities</dd>
  </dl>
  <div class="noprint">
    <address>
      <a href="http://www.iki.fi/marjola/">
        Homepage of the
        Author
      </a>
    </address>
  </div>
</gamedesign>
